We're going to take a look at the hierarchical file system of ZOS UNIX and understand its structure, concepts, and uses.
There's a lot to cover here, so we've broken this up into multiple sections. Stick with me.
Once we've established these file system fundamentals, we can really move on to the fun stuff of utilities, commands, and
functions. So
let's get started.
The ZOS UNIX file system is
hierarchical in structure in the same way as a UNIX file system is. All files are members of a directory and
each directory is in turn a member of another directory at a higher level in the hierarchy.
The highest level in the hierarchy is called the root directory. A file in the hierarchical file system is called an HFS file.
HFS files are byte oriented and there's no concept of a record structure. A
file system is contained in a ZOS data set called a hierarchical file system or HFS data set.
ZOS views an entire file system hierarchy as a collection of HFS data sets and
ZFS data sets. Each HFS data set is a mountable file system.
Connecting one file system to another is called mounting.
HFS and ZFS data sets can be mounted onto each other in the hierarchy.
The root file system is the first file system mounted and then subsequent file systems can be mounted on any directory within the root
file system or on a directory within any mounted file system.
The place within a file system where another file system is mounted is called a mount point.
A file system can be mounted only in one place at a time.
The mount command is used to mount a file system and unmount is used to disconnect a file system from the file system hierarchy.
Mount and unmount are both authorized commands.
The root file system is the starting point of the overall file system and it consists of the root directory
which is just a forward slash and
related directories and files.
The system programmer defines the root file system. The root file system usually contains
system related files and files that belong to a program product.
The root file system should be kept as non-volatile as possible.
It can be unmounted and remounted, but this activity really should be kept to a minimum.
User files are often located in other mountable file systems.
Altogether, the root file system and the mountable file systems contain the file systems used by shell users and by applications.
There's a temporary file system or TFS which can be mounted at slash TMP.
This file system type avoids physical I.O. since all files are kept in memory and such files are not kept permanently.
Because of its temporary nature and use of memory instead of I.O. TMP is a good option for users and
system temporary files.
The set of names required to specify a particular file in a hierarchy of directories is called the path to the file.
The path is specified as a path name. A path name can be absolute or it can be relative.
An absolute path name is a sequence which begins with a slash for the root followed by one or more directories and ends with the file name.
A relative path name is a path which is relative to the working directory.
A relative path name does not start with a slash.
Now, a path name can be up to 1023 characters long, including all directory names, separating slashes and the file name itself.
And a file name can be up to 255 characters long and consist of uppercase and lowercase letters.
As we mentioned before, ZOS Unix is case sensitive, so watch out for that.
File names can include extensions which identify the contents for a file, for example,
prog A.C or name.LST.
Now next up, we're going to turn our attention to file types.